<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="//h2481931.stratoserver.net:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="//h2481931.stratoserver.net:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-04-19T16:53:10+00:00</updated><id>//h2481931.stratoserver.net:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">rightsstatements</title><author><name>rightsstatements.org</name></author><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Do the rights statements apply to works, digital representations of works or both?</title><link href="//h2481931.stratoserver.net:4000/en/2018/12/where-statements-apply.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do the rights statements apply to works, digital representations of works or both?" /><published>2018-12-21T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-12-21T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>//h2481931.stratoserver.net:4000/en/2018/12/where-statements-apply</id><content type="html" xml:base="//h2481931.stratoserver.net:4000/en/2018/12/where-statements-apply.html">&lt;p&gt;One of the most frequently asked questions about the rightsstatements.org statements is if they apply to &lt;em&gt;original works&lt;/em&gt; (i.e. a painting) or the &lt;em&gt;digital objects&lt;/em&gt; (i.e. a specific digital representation of the painting in the form of an image file).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our statements have been purposively designed so that they can be applied to &lt;em&gt;digital objects&lt;/em&gt; to make it easier for users of the &lt;em&gt;digital objects&lt;/em&gt; to determine the copyright and reuse status. This design process and principles are documented in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsstatements.org/en/documentation/rights-statements-white-paper/&quot;&gt;right statements white paper&lt;/a&gt;. The primary use case would be a cultural heritage institution that displays a rights statement next to a &lt;em&gt;digital object&lt;/em&gt; on its website. In this scenario the statement indicates the copyright and reuse information of that &lt;em&gt;digital object&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition most of our statements can also be used to indicate the copyright status of &lt;em&gt;original works&lt;/em&gt;. For example a website may want to use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsstatements.org/vocab/InC/1.0/&quot;&gt;In Copyright statement&lt;/a&gt; to indicate that a book is in copyright without providing access to a specific digital representation of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most often the &lt;em&gt;digital object&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;original work&lt;/em&gt; will have the same copyright status. However it is worth worth bearing in mind the realities of the digitisation process. In many jurisdictions, additional copyrights, permissions and restrictions that affect the status of the &lt;em&gt;digital object&lt;/em&gt; can be created during as a result of acquisition or the process of digitising an &lt;em&gt;original work&lt;/em&gt;. As a matter of policy and practice we strongly believe that digitisation should not create a new layer of restrictions, and to the extent that restrictions are created, those should be waived. In situations where such additional rights or restrictions do exist, this should be reflected by rights statements that are applied at the level of the &lt;em&gt;digital object&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that as our statements have been designed to reflect the status of a &lt;em&gt;digital object&lt;/em&gt;, most of them can also be used to describe the copyright and status of the &lt;em&gt;original work&lt;/em&gt;. We’ve broken this down along with some exceptions to this below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rights-statements-for-in-copyright-objects&quot;&gt;Rights statements for in copyright objects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following three statements refer to the copyright status of both the &lt;em&gt;digital object&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;original work&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsstatements.org/vocab/InC/1.0/&quot;&gt;In Copyright&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsstatements.org/vocab/InC-OW-EU/1.0/&quot;&gt;In Copyright - EU Orphan Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsstatements.org/vocab/InC-RUU/1.0/&quot;&gt;In Copyright - Rights-holder(s) Unlocatable or Unidentifiable&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining two statements describe additional permissions on top of the copyright status, which apply only to the &lt;em&gt;digital object&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsstatements.org/vocab/InC-EDU/1.0/&quot;&gt;In Copyright - Educational Use Permitted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsstatements.org/vocab/InC-NC/1.0/&quot;&gt;In Copyright - Non-Commercial Use Permitted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, these statements can be used to indicate re-use conditions of &lt;em&gt;digital objects&lt;/em&gt; but should not be used for &lt;em&gt;original works&lt;/em&gt; (instead the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.creativecommons.org/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons licenses&lt;/a&gt; should be used for granting permissions to use copyrighted &lt;em&gt;works&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rights-statements-for-objects-that-are-not-in-copyright&quot;&gt;Rights statements for objects that are not in copyright&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this category the &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsstatements.org/vocab/NoC-US/1.0/&quot;&gt;No Copyright - United States&lt;/a&gt; refers to the copyright status of both the &lt;em&gt;original work&lt;/em&gt; and its &lt;em&gt;digital object&lt;/em&gt;. Unlike other statement in this category, no additional restrictions on reuse are expressed beyond its Public Domain status. It is also distinct because this public domain status depends on the physical location of the user of the &lt;em&gt;digital object&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining three statements indicate the status of the &lt;em&gt;digital object&lt;/em&gt; only. Each of these statements identifies restrictions or explicit permission that are different from the original out of copyright work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsstatements.org/vocab/NoC-CR/1.0/&quot;&gt;No Copyright - Contractual Restrictions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsstatements.org/vocab/NoC-NC/1.0/&quot;&gt;No Copyright - Non-Commercial Use&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsstatements.org/vocab/NoC-OKLR/1.0/&quot;&gt;No Copyright - Other Known Legal Restrictions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-rights-statements&quot;&gt;Other rights statements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three statements in this category can be used for the &lt;em&gt;original work&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;digital copies&lt;/em&gt; as the rights status is identical for both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsstatements.org/vocab/CNE/1.0/&quot;&gt;Copyright Not Evaluated&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsstatements.org/vocab/UND/1.0/&quot;&gt;Copyright Undetermined&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsstatements.org/vocab/NKC/1.0/&quot;&gt;No Known Copyright&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the new year we will publish a follow up post that will dive deeper into the technical details of how our statements can be applied to the different layers discussed in this post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>rightsstatements.org</name></author><summary type="html">One of the most frequently asked questions about the rightsstatements.org statements is if they apply to original works (i.e. a painting) or the digital objects (i.e. a specific digital representation of the painting in the form of an image file). Our statements have been purposively designed so that they can be applied to digital objects to make it easier for users of the digital objects to determine the copyright and reuse status. This design process and principles are documented in the right statements white paper. The primary use case would be a cultural heritage institution that displays a rights statement next to a digital object on its website. In this scenario the statement indicates the copyright and reuse information of that digital object. In addition most of our statements can also be used to indicate the copyright status of original works. For example a website may want to use the In Copyright statement to indicate that a book is in copyright without providing access to a specific digital representation of the book. Most often the digital object and the original work will have the same copyright status. However it is worth worth bearing in mind the realities of the digitisation process. In many jurisdictions, additional copyrights, permissions and restrictions that affect the status of the digital object can be created during as a result of acquisition or the process of digitising an original work. As a matter of policy and practice we strongly believe that digitisation should not create a new layer of restrictions, and to the extent that restrictions are created, those should be waived. In situations where such additional rights or restrictions do exist, this should be reflected by rights statements that are applied at the level of the digital object. This means that as our statements have been designed to reflect the status of a digital object, most of them can also be used to describe the copyright and status of the original work. We’ve broken this down along with some exceptions to this below. Rights statements for in copyright objects The following three statements refer to the copyright status of both the digital object and the original work: In Copyright In Copyright - EU Orphan Work In Copyright - Rights-holder(s) Unlocatable or Unidentifiable The remaining two statements describe additional permissions on top of the copyright status, which apply only to the digital object. In Copyright - Educational Use Permitted In Copyright - Non-Commercial Use Permitted As such, these statements can be used to indicate re-use conditions of digital objects but should not be used for original works (instead the Creative Commons licenses should be used for granting permissions to use copyrighted works). Rights statements for objects that are not in copyright In this category the No Copyright - United States refers to the copyright status of both the original work and its digital object. Unlike other statement in this category, no additional restrictions on reuse are expressed beyond its Public Domain status. It is also distinct because this public domain status depends on the physical location of the user of the digital object. The remaining three statements indicate the status of the digital object only. Each of these statements identifies restrictions or explicit permission that are different from the original out of copyright work. No Copyright - Contractual Restrictions No Copyright - Non-Commercial Use No Copyright - Other Known Legal Restrictions Other rights statements All three statements in this category can be used for the original work and digital copies as the rights status is identical for both. Copyright Not Evaluated Copyright Undetermined No Known Copyright In the new year we will publish a follow up post that will dive deeper into the technical details of how our statements can be applied to the different layers discussed in this post.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">A few changes at the rightsstatements.org consortium</title><link href="//h2481931.stratoserver.net:4000/en/2018/07/consortium-changes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A few changes at the rightsstatements.org consortium" /><published>2018-07-18T14:50:37+00:00</published><updated>2018-07-18T14:50:37+00:00</updated><id>//h2481931.stratoserver.net:4000/en/2018/07/consortium-changes</id><content type="html" xml:base="//h2481931.stratoserver.net:4000/en/2018/07/consortium-changes.html">&lt;p&gt;In June’s annual meeting of the steering committee, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kl.nl/en/people/paul-keller/&quot;&gt;Paul Keller&lt;/a&gt; - on behalf of &lt;a href=&quot;https://pro.europeana.eu/&quot;&gt;Europeana Foundation&lt;/a&gt; - was elected chair of the consortium.  Paul is the Director of Dutch think tank Kennisland, and a member of the Europeana Foundation, and Network Association Governing Boards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The renewal of consortium chair follows the departure of co-founder &lt;a href=&quot;https://pro.europeana.eu/person/jill-cousins&quot;&gt;Jill Cousins&lt;/a&gt;. Paul is supported in his role by  Vice-Chair, Caitlin Horrall of &lt;a href=&quot;https://nhds.ca/&quot;&gt;Library &amp;amp; Archives Canada&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d like to thank Jill - and fellow co-founder and ex-chair of the DPLA, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dan_Cohen_(academic)&quot;&gt;Dan Cohen&lt;/a&gt; for their work in creating the vision for the consortium, and starting us on the path towards becoming a firmly established global standard in the cultural heritage sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, in July &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/GregCram&quot;&gt;Greg Cram&lt;/a&gt; was been elected co-chair of the Statements Working Group.  Greg is the Associate Director of Copyright and Information Policy for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/odtspoGmpH&quot;&gt;NYPL&lt;/a&gt;, involved in the development of the consortium since its inception and is a keen advocate for the take up on statements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The position of co-chair of the Statement Working Group was previously held by Paul Keller, alongside current co-chair Emily Gore.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>rightsstatements.org</name></author><summary type="html">In June’s annual meeting of the steering committee, Paul Keller - on behalf of Europeana Foundation - was elected chair of the consortium. Paul is the Director of Dutch think tank Kennisland, and a member of the Europeana Foundation, and Network Association Governing Boards. The renewal of consortium chair follows the departure of co-founder Jill Cousins. Paul is supported in his role by Vice-Chair, Caitlin Horrall of Library &amp;amp; Archives Canada. We’d like to thank Jill - and fellow co-founder and ex-chair of the DPLA, Dan Cohen for their work in creating the vision for the consortium, and starting us on the path towards becoming a firmly established global standard in the cultural heritage sector. In addition, in July Greg Cram was been elected co-chair of the Statements Working Group. Greg is the Associate Director of Copyright and Information Policy for the NYPL, involved in the development of the consortium since its inception and is a keen advocate for the take up on statements. The position of co-chair of the Statement Working Group was previously held by Paul Keller, alongside current co-chair Emily Gore.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">German and Estonian translations now available for use</title><link href="//h2481931.stratoserver.net:4000/en/2018/06/translations.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="German and Estonian translations now available for use" /><published>2018-06-08T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-06-08T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>//h2481931.stratoserver.net:4000/en/2018/06/translations</id><content type="html" xml:base="//h2481931.stratoserver.net:4000/en/2018/06/translations.html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the rightsstatements.org blog!  We will use this blog to share information about the development of rightsstatements.org and about the resources that can help you implementing our rights statements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re happy to start with the great news that the official translations of all 12 statements into &lt;a href=&quot;http://rightsstatements.org/page/1.0/?language=de&quot;&gt;German&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://rightsstatements.org/page/1.0/?language=et&quot;&gt;Estonian&lt;/a&gt; are now published and available for everyone to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d like to thank &lt;a href=&quot;https://pro.europeana.eu/person/ellen-euler&quot;&gt;Ellen Euler&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iljabraun.de/&quot;&gt;Ilja Braun&lt;/a&gt; for being the first volunteer and working with us to develop the German translation, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pro.europeana.eu/person/vahur-puik&quot;&gt;Vahur Pruik&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etis.ee/CV/Tanel_Pern/est&quot;&gt;Tanel Pern&lt;/a&gt; for their work delivering the Estonian translation. We would also like to thank everyone else who contributed to these translations via the public review or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the translated version of the statements don’t require any extra work. If your browser language is set to German or Estonian, you will automatically see the statements in your chosen language.  Alternatively you can browse the &lt;a href=&quot;http://rightsstatements.org/de/&quot;&gt;German&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://rightsstatements.org/et/&quot;&gt;Estonian&lt;/a&gt; pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;upcoming-translations&quot;&gt;Upcoming translations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We currently have Portuguese, Spanish, Finnish, Swedish, Finland Swedish and Polish translations of the statements underway. All official translations are undertaken by volunteers following our &lt;a href=&quot;http://rightsstatements.org/en/documentation/translations.html&quot;&gt;translations policy&lt;/a&gt;.  Once an application has progressed through the quality control steps laid out in the policy, the translations are published on rightsstatements.org. If you are interested in providing an official translation, please contact us at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:info@rightsstatements.org&quot;&gt;info@rightsstatements.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>rightsstatements.org</name></author><summary type="html">Welcome to the rightsstatements.org blog! We will use this blog to share information about the development of rightsstatements.org and about the resources that can help you implementing our rights statements. We’re happy to start with the great news that the official translations of all 12 statements into German and Estonian are now published and available for everyone to use. We’d like to thank Ellen Euler and Ilja Braun for being the first volunteer and working with us to develop the German translation, and Vahur Pruik and Tanel Pern for their work delivering the Estonian translation. We would also like to thank everyone else who contributed to these translations via the public review or otherwise. Using the translated version of the statements don’t require any extra work. If your browser language is set to German or Estonian, you will automatically see the statements in your chosen language. Alternatively you can browse the German and Estonian pages. Upcoming translations We currently have Portuguese, Spanish, Finnish, Swedish, Finland Swedish and Polish translations of the statements underway. All official translations are undertaken by volunteers following our translations policy. Once an application has progressed through the quality control steps laid out in the policy, the translations are published on rightsstatements.org. If you are interested in providing an official translation, please contact us at info@rightsstatements.org.</summary></entry></feed>